Guide to the Theodore and Ruth Lidz Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- General files, 1939-2000, undated; Series II
  - Matussek, Paul, 1972-1990 (Box 11, Folder 239)
  - Mayson, Sterrett, 1972-1973 (Box 11, Folder 240)
  - Mboya, Mzobanzi, 1989 (Box 11, Folder 241)
  - McClary, Allan R., 1951-1973 (Box 11, Folder 242)
  - McGraw-Hill Book Company, Inc., 1948-1980 (Box 11, Folder 243)
  - McKenzie, Janice Marilyn, 1971 (Box 11, Folder 244)
  - Medical Committee for Human Rights, 1971-1972 (Box 11, Folder 245)
  - Mendell, David, 1968-1970 (Box 11, Folder 246)
  - Meninger Foundation, 1954-1972 (Box 11, Folder 247)
  - Meyer, Eugene, 1952-1976 (Box 11, Folder 248)
  - Meyer, J.-E., 1967-1982 (Box 11, Folder 249)
  - Midwest Professors of Psychiatry annual meeting, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 250)
  - Minuchin, Salvador, 1970-1976 (Box 11, Folder 251)
  - Mirsky, L. Arthur, 1955-1974 (Box 11, Folder 252)
  - Mitscherlich, Alexander, 1969-1974 (Box 11, Folder 253)
  - Moses, Leon, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 254)
  - Mosher, Loren, 1965-1972 (Box 11, Folder 255)
  - Mount Sinai Hospital, [New York, N.Y.], 1951-1952 (Box 11, Folder 256)
  - Müller, Christian, 1970-1986 (Box 11, Folder 257)
  - Muncie, Wendell, 1946-1973 (Box 11, Folder 258)
  - Musto, David F., 1967-1970 (Box 11, Folder 259)
  - Myers, J. Martin, 1966-1976 (Box 11, Folder 260)
  - N, 1952-1991 (Box 11, Folder 261-262)
  - Nahum, Jeremy P., 1966-1971 (Box 11, Folder 263)
  - Nakhala, Fayek, 1967-1968 (Box 11, Folder 264)
  - National Institute of Mental Health, 1954-1972 (Box 11, Folder 265)
  - Nemiah, John C. II, 1968-1991 (Box 11, Folder 266)
  - Nemiroff, Robert A., 1970-1987 (Box 11, Folder 267)
  - Nixon, Richard M., 1970-1973 (Box 11, Folder 268)
  - Norris, Charles and Ruth, 1970-1985 (Box 11, Folder 269)
  - O, 1954-1989 (Box 11, Folder 270)
  - Olsson, James E., 1971-1972 (Box 12, Folder 271)
  - Orrill, Robert, 1970-1971 (Box 12, Folder 272)
  - P, 1951-1991 (Box 12, Folder 273-276)
  - Parents Association for Childbirth Education, 1972-1973 (Box 12, Folder 277)
  - Parker, Beulah II, 1954-1984 (Box 12, Folder 278)
  - Paul, Robert A., 1987-1988 (Box 12, Folder 279)
  - Pelleteri, Virginia Bassi, 1989-1990 (Box 12, Folder 280)
  - Peters, Uwe Henrik, 1982-1989 (Box 12, Folder 281)
  - Pilot, Martin L., 1954-1969, undated (Box 12, Folder 282)
  - Pine, Irving, 1967-1971 (Box 12, Folder 283)
  - Plaut, Jules and Ellen, 1952-1979 (Box 12, Folder 284)
  - Pollock, George, 1971-1991 (Box 12, Folder 285)
  - Polsby, Nelson, 1968-1969 (Box 12, Folder 286)
  - Poole, Fitz John Porter, 1984-1988 (Box 13, Folder 287)
  - Pospisil, Leopold, 1982-1988 (Box 13, Folder 288)
  - Psychoanalytic Review, 1984-1987 (Box 13, Folder 289)
  - Psychosomatic Medicine, 1952-1967 (Box 13, Folder 290)
  - Q, 1968-1990 (Box 13, Folder 291)
  - R, 1952-1990 (Box 13, Folder 292-294)
  - Raybin, James B., 1968-1971 (Box 13, Folder 295)
  - Recommendations, 196--1991 (Box 14, Folder 296-305)
    Restricted until January 1, 2066 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
  - Redlich, Frederick C. II, 1948-1978 (Box 15, Folder 306-308)
  - Reich, Walter, 1974-1989 (Box 15, Folder 309)
  - Reiser, Morton F. II, 1954-1983 (Box 15, Folder 310)
  - Ribicoff, Abe, 1968-1975 (Box 15, Folder 311)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1987 (Box 15, Folder 312)
  - Romano, John, 1951-1979 (Box 15, Folder 313)
  - Rose, Gilbert, 1967-1990 (Box 15, Folder 314)
  - Rosen, Harold, 1951-1973 (Box 15, Folder 315)
  - Rosen, Victor, 1953-1971 (Box 15, Folder 316)
  - Rosenbaum, C. Peter, 1967-1975 (Box 15, Folder 317)
  - Rosenbaum, Milton, 1953-1976 (Box 15, Folder 318)
  - Rosenthal, Arthur, 1970-1986 (Box 15, Folder 319)
  - Rothenberg, Albert, 1966-1991 (Box 15, Folder 320)
  - Rubenstein, Robert, 1967-1975 (Box 15, Folder 321)
  - Rubin, Alex, 1951 (Box 15, Folder 322)
  - Rubinstein, David, 1970-1975 (Box 15, Folder 323)
  - Rubinstein, Irvin, 1965-1978 (Box 15, Folder 324)
  - Ruskay family, 1969-1975 (Box 15, Folder 325)
  - S-Sp, 1951-1991 (Box 15, Folder 326-332)
  - St-Sz, 1951-1991 (Box 16, Folder 333-334)
  - S. Fischer Verlag, 1970-1976 (Box 16, Folder 335)
  - Sander, Fred, 1966-1990 (Box 16, Folder 336)
  - Schwartz, Daniel P., 1984-1988 (Box 16, Folder 337)
  - Second Conference on Psychiatric Education. Special Commission on Psychodynamic Principles, 1951 (Box 16, Folder 338-341)
  - Seifer, Ronald L., 1969-1970 (Box 16, Folder 342)
  - Sewell, Richard B., 1968-1970 (Box 16, Folder 343)
  - Shannon, Karr, 1969-1971 (Box 16, Folder 344)
  - Sheps, Jack, 1970-1972 (Box 16, Folder 345)
  - Silver, Anne-Louise, 1985-1988 (Box 16, Folder 346)
  - Sluzki, Carlos, 1969-1990 (Box 16, Folder 347)
  - Society of Medical Psychoanalysts, 1970-1972 (Box 16, Folder 348)
  - Solnit, Albert J., 1968-1989 (Box 16, Folder 349)
  - State University of New York. Downstate Medical Center, 1972-1985 (Box 16, Folder 350)
  - Stierlin, Helm, 1966-1991 (Box 16, Folder 351)
  - Stone, Walter N., 1969-1970 (Box 16, Folder 352)
  - Story, R. Ian, 1968-1972 (Box 16, Folder 353)
  - Stubblefield, Robert, 1984-1990 (Box 16, Folder 354)
  - Stunkard, Albert J., 1968-1990 (Box 16, Folder 355)
  - Sutherland, Arthur W., 1952-1953 (Box 16, Folder 356)
  - Suzuki, Koji, 1967-1990 (Box 16, Folder 357)
  - T, 1948-1990 (Box 16, Folder 358-359)
  - Thomä, Helmut, 1967-1991 (Box 17, Folder 360)
  - Tienari, Pekka, 1982-1990 (Box 17, Folder 361)
  - U, 1951-1990 (Box 17, Folder 362-363)
  - Ugelstad, Endre, 1975-1990 (Box 17, Folder 364)
  - University of Chicago Press, 1986-1987 (Box 17, Folder 365)
  - University of Maryland, 1969 (Box 17, Folder 366)
  - University of Virginia, 1970-1971 (Box 17, Folder 367)
  - Ursano, Robert J., 1984-1991 (Box 17, Folder 368)
  - V, 1967-1990 (Box 17, Folder 369)
  - Vanggard, Thorkill, 1971-1972 (Box 17, Folder 370)
  - Van Nuffel, Dirk, 1973-1989 (Box 17, Folder 371)
  - Vaughn, Beulah Parker
    See: Series II, Box 12, Folder 278
  - Vogel, Ezra F., 1967-1973 (Box 17, Folder 372)
  - Vosberg, Robert, 1974-1975 (Box 17, Folder 373)
  - W, 1949-1991 (Box 17, Folder 374-379)
  - Wang, Richard P., 1970-1973 (Box 17, Folder 380)
  - Weicker, Lowell, 1972-1987 (Box 17, Folder 381)
  - Weigert, Edith, 1950-1976 (Box 17, Folder 382)
  - Werner, Sidney C., 1952-1974 (Box 17, Folder 383)
  - Wexler, Henry, 1953-1972 (Box 17, Folder 384)
  - Whitehorn, John C., 1951-1973 (Box 17, Folder 385)
  - Will, Otto Allen, 1969-1975 (Box 17, Folder 386)
  - Wilmer, Harry A., 1967-1974 (Box 17, Folder 387)
  - Wood, Edwin C., 1955-1974 (Box 17, Folder 388)
  - World Congress of Psychiatry, Vth, 1970-1971 (Box 17, Folder 389)
  - World Federation for Mental Health, II, 1989-1990 (Box 17, Folder 390)
    See also: Series II, Box 5, Folder 78
  - World Psychiatric Association, 1974-1975 (Box 17, Folder 391)
  - Wright, David M., 1968-1973 (Box 17, Folder 392)
  - Wynne, Lyman C., 1967-1974 (Box 17, Folder 393)
  - Y, 1952-1990 (Box 18, Folder 394)
  - Yale-New Haven Hospital, 1982-1988 (Box 18, Folder 395)
  - Yale Psychiatric Institute, 1974-1990 (Box 18, Folder 396)
  - Yale University
    - General, 1952-1990 (Box 18, Folder 397)
      See also: Series II, Box 15, Folders 306-308
    - Faculty Study Group on Children, 1972 (Box 18, Folder 398)
    - School of Medicine
      - General, 1951-1991 (Box 18, Folder 399-401)
      - Committee on Governance, 1975 (Box 18, Folder 402)
      - Department of Psychiatry
        See also: Series II, box 15, folder 310
        - Annual reports, 1952-1978 (Box 18, Folder 403)
        - "Comprehensive Guide to Courses and Seminars", 1973 (Box 18, Folder 404)
        - "A Draft of a Program for Research in Schizophrenia", 1965 (Box 18, Folder 405)
        - Problem-Oriented-Record Task Committee [report], 1974 (Box 18, Folder 406)
        - Residency Clinical Research and Teaching Track, Behavioral Sciences and Psychiatry Track [draft], 1973 (Box 18, Folder 407)
        - Visitors, 1968-1969 (Box 18, Folder 408-409)
    - Residency training, 1966-1968 (Box 18, Folder 410)
  - Yale University Press, 1969-1991 (Box 18, Folder 411)
  - Yassky, Alfred D., 1972-1990 (Box 18, Folder 412)
  - Young, Harbin Bouterline, 1968-1977 (Box 18, Folder 413)
  - Z, 1954-1989 (Box 18, Folder 414)
  - Unidentified, 197--1989, undated (Box 18, Folder 415)
- Writings and Research, 1936-2000; Series III
  This series includes documentation concerning Theodore Lidz's publications and speeches, as well as research materials compiled over his professional career. Lidz's interest in schizophrenia looms large in this writing and research, but there is also material on New Guinea, the role of the family, and training for psychiatrists. It is not clear what percentage of Lidz's publications are represented. The available bibliographies (see Series V) end in the 1980s, although Lidz continued to publish after that date. As a general rule, drafts and reprints of published titles have not been retained. Lectures delivered to classes are included in Series IV, Teaching.
  The series is divided into several sections. The section Books contains manuscripts for unpublished works, correspondence associated with a title, and book reviews. Books are listed alphabetically by title. "To Carve a Space Out of Chaos" contains published papers as well as an autobiographical "Epilogue." "Youth: A Critical Passage" is also autobiographical, and in it Lidz discusses the influence of his father's death. "Our Stone Age Contemporaries" describes customs of the Papua new Guinea peoples.
  The section's other writings includes materials about published papers, chapters contributed to monographs, book reviews, letters to the editor, and the like, while the section Lectures and other presentations includes similar materials for talks, presentations at professional meetings, remarks at conference sessions, and interviews. Many of these contain untitled and/or undated typescripts or reading notes. Titles shown with quotation marks are those shown on the manuscript. Where Lidz provided no title, an assigned subject is shown in the listing. The dated items are arranged chronologically. Those without dates [noted as 'no date'] are arranged alphabetically by title or subject at the end. The Notes section, arranged alphabetically by subject, includes Lidz's reasoned analysis of readings, both literary and psychiatric, that he most likely created in preparation for writings or lectures.
  The Research files include studies of various medical and psychological problems that might affect the mental states of patients and selected patient files from Lidz's private practice. The most substantive materials are those on families, compiled as part of Lidz's work on Schizophrenia and the Family. The data includes excerpts of hospital records, correspondence, psychological tests of the patient and members of the immediate family, summaries of the individual cases, and transcripts of family group meetings. The detailed investigations describe current psychoanalytic insights, techniques for testing, and therapy by a group of established experts. For Lidz, these confirmed the influence of the family environment in causing schizophrenia. Creative efforts by the patient, such as poems, drawings, and writings, are included in some case studies. To protect confidentiality, the study's researchers referred to the families using coded names. The family names used in this register are the coded version of the real name. The data section also contains additional family materials, including private patient cases that may have been retained to provide data for other projects. The section reflects Lidz's own arrangement in keeping these files together. The names are listed by initials or a truncated form of the family name.
  - Books
    - The Family and Human Adaptation, 1963-1964 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Hamlet's Enemy, 1975-1980 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Oedipus in the Stone Age, 1989 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - The Origins and Treatment of Schizophrenic Disorders, 1973 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - "Our Stone-Age Contemporaries"
      - Manuscript, 1973? (Box 19, Folder 5-11)
      - Evaluation, 197- (Box 19, Folder 12)
    - The Person
      - Correspondence re comments on advertising, 1976 (Box 19, Folder 13)
      - Introduction to the revised edition, 1977 (Box 19, Folder 14)
      - Reviews, 1968-1969 (Box 19, Folder 15)
    - The Relevance of the Family to Psychoanalytic Theory, 1992-1993 (Box 19, Folder 16)
    - Schizophrenia and the Family, 1965-1966 (Box 19, Folder 17)
    - "To Carve a Space Out of Chaos", [2000? (Box 19, Folder 18-20)
    - "To Carve a Space Out of Chaos", [2000? (Box 20, Folder 21-23)
    - Training Tomorrow's Psychiatrists, 1970 (Box 20, Folder 24)
    - "Youth: A Critical Passage", 199- (Box 20, Folder 25)
  - Other writings
    - Book reviews, 1947-1986 (Box 20, Folder 26-27)
    - "Psychiatric Problems in a Thyroid Clinic" [with J. C. Whitehorn], 1948 (Box 20, Folder 28)
    - Joint Council of the Psychiatric Societies of Maryland [report, correspondence] III, 1949 (Box 20, Folder 29)
    - "An Interpretation of the Perspectives of American Psychiatry" [translation of paper published in German, with R.W. Lidz] III, 1950 (Box 20, Folder 30)
    - "Report to the National Research Council on Psychiatry" [concerning screening procedures used at induction centers as an adjunct to psychiatric interviews], 1952 (Box 20, Folder 31)
    - "Psychophysiological Properties of the Adrenal Cortex" [panel discussion, A.P.S. meeting], 1953 (Box 20, Folder 32)
    - "Psychiatric Aspects of Dietetics", 1953? (Box 20, Folder 33)
    - "The Role of the Father in the Family Environment of the Schizophrenic Patient" [Johns Hopkins, with B. Parker, et. al.], 1955] (Box 20, Folder 34)
    - "The Contribution of Psychiatric Medicine to Ward Problems", 1959] (Box 20, Folder 35)
    - Guadalcanal, 195- (Box 20, Folder 36)
    - "Gaia", 1961 (Box 20, Folder 37)
    - "The Family, Language, and Schizophrenia", 1968? (Box 20, Folder 38)
    - "The Family, Human Adaptation, and Ethics", 196- (Box 20, Folder 39)
    - "Schizophrenia--Thoughts on Etiology", 1970 (Box 20, Folder 40)
    - New York Times [letters to the editor], 1972-1998 (Box 21, Folder 41)
    - Cameron, Norman A. [obituary], 1975] (Box 21, Folder 42)
    - Danish adoption studies by Rosenthal, Kety, and Wender, 1978] (Box 21, Folder 43-44)
    - "The Developing Guidelines to the Psychotherapy of Schizophrenia", 197- (Box 21, Folder 45)
    - Family studies and psychoanalytic theories, 197- (Box 21, Folder 46)
    - "Some Comments on the Supervision of the Psychotherapy of Schizophrenic Patients" [with R.W. Lidz] III, 197- (Box 21, Folder 47)
    - Theory of schizophrenic disorders, 197- (Box 21, Folder 48)
    - Response to Lowing, et. al. [letter to an editor], 1983 (Box 21, Folder 49)
    - "The Determinants of the Psychiatric Syndrome", 1989 (Box 21, Folder 50)
    - "The Dreams in Wild Strawberries, 1989 (Box 21, Folder 51)
    - "Sorcery and Societal Integration in Papua New Guinea" [with R.W. Lidz] III, 1989 (Box 21, Folder 52)
    - Daniel Weinberger's article in Psych News, 1989] (Box 21, Folder 53)
    - " Wild Strawberries in the Light of Bergman's Autobiography", 1989? (Box 21, Folder 54)
    - "Genetic and Psychosocial Evolution and the Future of Psychiatry", 198- (Box 21, Folder 55)
    - "A Psychosocial Orientation to the Study of Schizophrenic Disorders", 198- (Box 21, Folder 56)
    - "A Psychoanalytic Reading of Hamlet " [E. Weigert's seventy-fifth birthday], 1990 (Box 21, Folder 57)
    - New concepts of schizophrenic disorders, 1996 (Box 21, Folder 58)
    - "...Schiz. '97 Reformulation", 1997? (Box 21, Folder 59)
    - Intrafamilial environment of psychiatric patients, 1998 (Box 21, Folder 60)
    - "Schizophrenia and Preoperational Thinking", 1998 (Box 21, Folder 61)
    - Language of schizophrenia, 1998, undated (Box 21, Folder 62)
    - "Concerning the Studies of Schizophrenic Thought Disorders", 199- (Box 21, Folder 63)
    - Skrabanek's article, 199- (Box 21, Folder 64)
    - "Strange Encounters, Dreams, and Nightmares of High School Students in Papua New Guinea", 199- (Box 21, Folder 65)
    - "Anthropology and Religion", undated (Box 21, Folder 66)
    - "Changing Psychiatric Training" [summary], undated (Box 21, Folder 67)
    - "Concepts of Etiology", undated (Box 21, Folder 68)
    - Dr. Leff's paper, undated (Box 21, Folder 69)
    - Etiology of schizophrenia, undated (Box 21, Folder 70)
    - "Factors Concerning the Recovery of Patients Treated with the Aid of Shock Therapy" [with R. W. Lidz] III, undated (Box 21, Folder 71)
    - "The Family and the Self", undated (Box 21, Folder 72)
    - "The Family Background of Schizophrenics", undated (Box 21, Folder 73)
    - Family in psychoanalytic theory, undated (Box 21, Folder 74)
    - Family, myth, and ethics [fragment], undated (Box 21, Folder 75)
    - "The Human Endowment", undated (Box 21, Folder 76)
    - Hypertension materials, undated (Box 21, Folder 77)
    - "The Intrapsychic and the Environmental", undated (Box 21, Folder 78)
    - Male menstruation, undated (Box 22, Folder 79)
    - "Marital Interaction, Family Organization, and the Personality Structure of Children", undated (Box 22, Folder 80)
    - Mothers of schizophrenic patients, undated (Box 22, Folder 81)
    - New Guinea paper, undated (Box 22, Folder 82)
    - Phases of masculine identity in New Guinea, undated (Box 22, Folder 83)
    - "The Preschool vs. Oedipal Child", undated (Box 22, Folder 84)
    - "Psychiatry and the Family", undated (Box 22, Folder 85)
    - Psychoanalysis and the family, undated (Box 22, Folder 86)
    - "Psychoanalytic and Sociological Concepts of Religion", undated (Box 22, Folder 87)
    - "The Psychosomatic Approach to Medicine", undated (Box 22, Folder 88)
    - "Psychosomatic Medicine of the Gastrointestinal System", undated (Box 22, Folder 89)
    - Relationship between upbringing and schizophrenia, undated (Box 22, Folder 90)
    - Relationship of cargo cults to psychopathology, undated (Box 22, Folder 91)
    - "Schizophrenia, the Family, and Psychoanalytic Theory", undated (Box 22, Folder 92)
    - Schizophrenic disorders, undated (Box 22, Folder 93)
    - "Schizophrenic Thinking and Creative Thought", undated (Box 22, Folder 94)
    - "The Schizophrenic Thought Disorder" [fragments], undated (Box 22, Folder 95)
    - "The Sensor's Tragedy", undated (Box 22, Folder 96)
    - "A Sketch of a Theory of Schizophrenic Disorders", undated (Box 22, Folder 97)
    - Theory of psychiatric disorders, undated (Box 22, Folder 98)
    - A theory of the nature and etiology of schizophrenia, undated (Box 22, Folder 99)
    - Troubled youth, undated (Box 22, Folder 100)
    - "Vietnam and Mental Health", undated (Box 22, Folder 101)
    - Unidentified fragments, undated (Box 22, Folder 102)
  - Lectures and other presentations
    - Amnestic difficulties [Henry Phipps Psychiatric Clinic], 1941 (Box 23, Folder 103)
    - Psychiatry in the changing world [Eighteenth General Hospital], 1944] (Box 23, Folder 104)
    - Child Study Association radio broadcast [transcript], 1948 (Box 23, Folder 105)
    - "The Contribution of Psychosomatic Medicine to Medical Ward Problems" [University of Maryland], 1948 (Box 23, Folder 106)
    - "Emotional Factors in the Precipitation of Recurrent Diabetic Acidosis" [with Harold Rosen, American Psychosomatic Society], 1949 (Box 23, Folder 107)
    - "The Integration of Medical and Psychiatric Methods and Objectives in Treatment on a Medical Service" [with S. Fleck, Society for Research in Psychosomatic Problems], 1949 (Box 23, Folder 108)
    - Psychosomatic service [HPPC Alumni meeting], 1949 (Box 23, Folder 109)
    - "Diabetes" [Walter Reed Hospital], 1950 (Box 23, Folder 110)
    - "The Conflict between Self Preservation and Social Demands in the War Neuroses" [Walter Reed Hospital], 1951 (Box 23, Folder 111)
    - "Principles and Techniques of Therapy in Psychosomatic Disorders" [Association of Nervous and Mental Disease], 1952 (Box 23, Folder 112)
    - "Chronic Situations Evoking Psychological Stress and the Common Signs of the Resulting Strain" [Symposium on Stress], 1953 (Box 23, Folder 113)
    - "Comments for Panel on the Indications and Contra-indications for the Termination of Pregnancy", 1953 (Box 23, Folder 114)
    - "Hypertension Paper for Analytic Meeting" [Round Table on Hypertension], 1953 (Box 23, Folder 115)
    - "Areas of Interdoctrinal Unacceptances" [discussion, First Conference on Mental Disease, New York Academy of Medicine], 1953-1955 (Box 23, Folder 116)
    - Conference on the Socio-environmental Aspects of Patient Treatment in Mental Hospitals, 1955 (Box 23, Folder 117)
    - "The Extra-hospital World of the Hospitalized Schizophrenic Patient" [Boston], 1955 (Box 23, Folder 118)
    - Headache panel [Connecticut Clinical Congress], 1955 (Box 23, Folder 119)
    - Hoedemaker's, "Further Studies on the Nature of the Therapeutic Process in Schizophrenia- Pre--analytic Preparation" [American Psychoanalytic Association], 1955 (Box 23, Folder 120)
    - "Ego Identification", 1956 (Box 23, Folder 121)
    - American Psychosomatic Society [presidential address], 1957 (Box 23, Folder 122)
    - "The Intrafamilial Environment of the Schizophrenic Patient" [presentation versions, American Psychiatric Association]
      - IV. The Transmission of Irrationality, 1957 (Box 23, Folder 123)
      - V. The Understanding of Symptomatology through the Study of the Family Interaction [with Fleck et. al.], 1957 (Box 23, Folder 124)
    - First Frieda Fromm-Reichmann Award [speech on receipt of award], 1961 (Box 23, Folder 125)
    - "Human Adaptation and the Family" [Tulane], 1961 (Box 23, Folder 126)
    - "The Human Mind: The Genetic and Cultural Endowment" [Yale alumni seminar], 1961 (Box 23, Folder 127)
    - "The Influence of the Family Environment" [panel], 1961 (Box 23, Folder 128)
    - "The Marital Relationship, Family Structure, and Personality Development" [Tulane], 1961 (Box 23, Folder 129)
    - "Differences between Male and Female Schizophrenic Patients" [University of Maryland], 1962 (Box 23, Folder 130)
    - Family therapy [American Orthopsychiatric Association], 1963 (Box 23, Folder 131)
    - Language [panel discussion, A. Ba. A. meeting], 1963 (Box 23, Folder 132)
    - Illinois State Psychiatric Institute. Mental Health and the Idea of Mankind [conference transcript, includes remarks made by T. Lidz], 1964 (Box 23, Folder 133-136)
    - Psychosomatic medicine [A. P. A. conference, Mexico], 1964 (Box 24, Folder 137)
    - "Adolf Meyer and the History of Psychiatry" [A. P. A. meeting, Atlantic City], 1965 (Box 24, Folder 138)
    - Federation lecture [San Francisco], 1965 (Box 24, Folder 139)
    - Sigma Xi initiation, 1965 (Box 24, Folder 140)
    - "Parental Interaction and Child Rearing" [summary, Chicago], 1966 (Box 24, Folder 141)
    - Comments on Atkin's paper [First Rochester International Conference], 1967 (Box 24, Folder 142)
    - Puerto Rico conference [discussion], 1967 (Box 24, Folder 143)
    - Salmon Lecture [notes], 1967] (Box 24, Folder 144)
    - "The Adolescent and the Family" [Taberoff Lecture, Utah], 1968 (Box 24, Folder 145)
    - "Body, Mind, Psyche" [Hartford Symposium], 1968 (Box 24, Folder 146)
    - "Der Einfluss von Familienuntersuchungen auf die Behandlung der Schizophrenie" [Twelfth Frieda Fromm-Reichmann Memorial Lecture], 1968 (Box 24, Folder 147)
    - The origin of schizophrenia [Puerto Rico, discussion], 1968 (Box 24, Folder 148)
    - "Marital Conflict" [Trumbull Symposium], 1969 (Box 24, Folder 149)
    - "What Troubles our Troubled Youth?" [Houston], 1970 (Box 24, Folder 150)
    - "The Nature and Origins of Schizophrenic Disorders" [William Menninger Award], 1972 (Box 24, Folder 151)